<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Code as Collage]]></title>
  <link href="http://ruthienachmany.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ruthienachmany.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-06-23T21:41:54-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://ruthienachmany.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ruthie Nachmany]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Reading Well]]></title>
    <link href="http://ruthienachmany.github.io/blog/2013/06/22/reading-well/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-22T17:58:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://ruthienachmany.github.io/blog/2013/06/22/reading-well</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Thought: A lot of learning to code is just learning to read code well</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sinatra]]></title>
    <link href="http://ruthienachmany.github.io/blog/2013/06/22/dd/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-22T16:20:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://ruthienachmany.github.io/blog/2013/06/22/dd</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Citibike Project Step 1: Understand MongoDB]]></title>
    <link href="http://ruthienachmany.github.io/blog/2013/06/18/hello-world/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-18T23:28:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://ruthienachmany.github.io/blog/2013/06/18/hello-world</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There are about 20 repos on Github that have to do with Citybike in some way (that I could find at least). Many of them use JSON and/or Python. Since I&rsquo;m still just starting to grasp Ruby, I decided to focus on mainly using the repos that use Ruby. I think the others can provide useful datasets and interesting outcomes I can learn from, but I don&rsquo;t think it would make sense to try to understand Python (apart from my new habit of tech talks with my 17 year old brother, who taught himself Python last summer and learned Java this year in school &ndash; and come to think of it, my new party conversation topics, which based on this weekend, focus on asking my programmer friends and what languages they use).</p>

<p>To use the Ruby repos I have to learn several other things. One repo I found is &ldquo;<a href="https://github.com/strcrzy/citibike.git">https://github.com/strcrzy/citibike.git</a>&rdquo;, which is &ldquo;a collection of ruby scripts that help scrape, slice, and dice the data available from the CitiBike API.&rdquo; To use it I need to use Mongoid, the Ruby ODM framework for MongoDB. It might not be the best strategy to use a repo that requires me to learn Mongo to understand what&rsquo;s going on on the inside, but we have Emily Stoflo, a Columbia professor and software engineer at 10gen, coming in to speak to us today in class, so it won&rsquo;t be a total waste of time. Interestingly, I learned about 10gen and MongoDB before I learned about SQL, based on my hackathon lurker activities while I was at Princeton, with 10gen as a sponsor (of the hackathon, not my lurking).</p>

<p>This all reminds me of some cool things that have been happening as I learn to program. I keep remembering all these other things that I&rsquo;ve heard of in the past that now I start to wonder what they really mean, and start to be able to contextualize that in a larger picture. I think that&rsquo;s part of the reason why I&rsquo;ve been so excited to talk about coding at parties, no joke. Everything starts to have new meaning and context.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m going to start tracking the new things that I learn, and the paths they lead down. Starting with Mongo&hellip;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[CitiBike Project: 'What is...' No. 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://ruthienachmany.github.io/blog/2013/06/18/what-is-dot-dot-dot/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-18T07:18:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://ruthienachmany.github.io/blog/2013/06/18/what-is-dot-dot-dot</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>What is MongoDB?
MongoDB is an open source document-oriented system developed and supported by 10gen. It&rsquo;s part of the NoSQL movement. As opposed to SQL, a relational databses, it structures data in JSON-like documents with dynamic schemas called BSONs. This can make MongoDB faster than SQL. At the same time, most people who use MongoDB used SQL for many years first, which I think is important to note. MTV, Craigslist, and Foursquare use MongoDB.</p>

<p>What is Mongoid?
Mongoid is an Object-Document-Mapper (ODM) for MongoDB, written in Ruby. It provides a familiar API to Ruby developers who have been using Active Record or Data Mapper, while leveraging MongoDB&rsquo;s schemaless document-based design, dynamic queries, and atomic modifier operations. (NOTE TO SELF: figure out what are atomic modifier operations)</p>

<p>What is JSON?
JSON is JavaScript Object Notation. It&rsquo;s a text-based open standard for human-readable data interchange, built on a collection of key-value pairs and arrays.  It comes from JavaScript objects, which represent simple data structures and associative arrays. Interestingly, though it references JavaScript, it is language-independent.</p>

<p>What is Active Record?
Active Record is a way to query databases in a SQL-like way in Rails without actually having to write SQL. It&rsquo;s compatible with MySWL, PostgreSQL, SQLite, and others.</p>

<p>DataMapper:
DataMapper is an Object-Relational-Mapper (ORM) for Ruby. It&rsquo;s  fast, thread-safe and feature rich. It differentiates itself by having one API for a variety of datastores, the ability to develop a data-store independently of models using Migrations (NOTE: figure out what this means), and helpful when querying or supporting data-stores you don&rsquo;t manage yourself, such as legacy databases.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Side Projects]]></title>
    <link href="http://ruthienachmany.github.io/blog/2013/06/17/side-projects/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-17T21:17:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://ruthienachmany.github.io/blog/2013/06/17/side-projects</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today marks the first day of my third week as a developer. This weekend was very transformative for me in terms of my growth and learning as a programmer. Thursday night I dreamed about code. Friday night marked the first gathering of the Flatiron School Drinking Club. I also learned how to DJ from my teacher at Fridays After Flatiron &ndash; learning to learn and all! These past two weeks, I&rsquo;ve been so inspired to learn new things or re-learn things I used to know. Every day presents a new idea &ndash; Relearn Japanese! Start DJing! Make a film! Run really far for a long time! Origami cranes! Tomorrow we&rsquo;re learning how to tie knots. Saturday I studied with classmates and learned from one how to play a Scandinavian version of bocci ball called Kubb. Sunday I rewrote code over and over again until the sounds got in my head. Today I really noticed today how much more fluent I was in Ruby syntax than last week. Then I saw Sacha Greif&rsquo;s &ldquo;Side Projects&rdquo; presentation on SpeakerDeck.</p>

<p>Greif makes awesome side projects. His presentation presents an argument for how and why.</p>

<p>Why should you work on side projects?</p>

<p>1) Build a product &ndash; learn how to bring an idea to execution and how to market it. Be your own CEO.
2) Learn something new &ndash; try out a cool new tool or framework
3) Get your name out there &ndash; can reach a lot of people &ndash; perhaps more than your regular work can</p>

<p>What makes a good side project?</p>

<p>1) Simple &ndash; be able to launch it in under 10 hours
2) Specific &ndash; solving well-defined need for specific target helps keep scope manageable &ndash; which is good practice in life in general
3) Special &ndash; have fun! stand out!</p>

<p>Find time</p>

<p>1) Scale down &ndash; if you can&rsquo;t increase time, decrease scope
2) Compromise &ndash; sacrifice some exercise, lunch, or sleep for one week to find those ten hours
3) Repurpose &ndash; take something you&rsquo;re doing anyway and make it your project</p>

<p>Don&rsquo;t overthink, overcomplexify, tell a story</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m so inspired by these mantras and I think that practicing good habits in small doses can reflect in positive ways on larger challenges and problem-solving activities I engage in on a daily basis. When I do Bikram yoga for an hour and a half, it&rsquo;s easier for me to run for 45 minutes. When I&rsquo;m hot in Bikram, I think about how hot it was to run in India. This goes on. Take your challenges and make them into tools. Build up habits in one field to another. Perhaps this is why this high-growth, high-learning last two weeks have inspired me to learn so many other things, and why so many of my learning and growth experiences have emerging as I problem solve in code. Writing code over and over again reminds me of writing poems I like over and over again to get the rhythm in my head.</p>

<p>I think of one of my favorite lines (though I have a lot of favorite lines):</p>

<p>More than once I’ve felt like a small bug with the brain of a man, standing on a leaf floating through the blood vessels and veins in my own body. As I navigate through a leg or into a body cavity, I can clearly see the faults and the strengths of my current convictions – little vignettes in continuous action, like the Pirates of the Caribbean ride at Disneyland, a haunted house carved into my organs and muscles. Anyhow, every day of my life when I draw another picture, I think maybe I’m trying to find something inside me that needs a new script. Like crashing your motorcycle and waking up and wondering why your foot is over there in the gutter. As I get older, I regret the mistakes of my life even deeper. And I feel the following things even more: Hooray for Happiness! Hooray for Life! Hooray for Everything!
-Mark Mothersbaugh</p>

<p>And another:</p>

<p>‘If you opened people up, you would find landscapes; if you opened me up, you would find beaches. Many old people wish to tell their life. As an old filmmaker, with the enthusiasm and energy of my youth, I tried to find a style and a form to tell my memories, my encounters, the ups and downs of my life. I shot my film as a kaleidoscope, a collage, a fantasy.’ Agnès Varda</p>

<p>My motto:</p>

<p>&ldquo;It loved to happen&rdquo; -Marcus Aurelius</p>

<p>This week:
10 hours, 1 side project. I think it&rsquo;s going to be about Citibike. I just cloned so many Citibike repos&hellip; and perhaps it will inspire me to learn how to ride a bike. Practice being a beginner&hellip;</p>

<p>More to come.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Write Code Everyday]]></title>
    <link href="http://ruthienachmany.github.io/blog/2013/06/13/write-code-everyday/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-13T07:50:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://ruthienachmany.github.io/blog/2013/06/13/write-code-everyday</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[fractals]]></title>
    <link href="http://ruthienachmany.github.io/blog/2013/06/13/being-special/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-13T07:36:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://ruthienachmany.github.io/blog/2013/06/13/being-special</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[creativity and structure]]></title>
    <link href="http://ruthienachmany.github.io/blog/2013/06/13/creativity-and-structure/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-13T00:58:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://ruthienachmany.github.io/blog/2013/06/13/creativity-and-structure</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>hey
GUI
GUYS</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[mediums you think in]]></title>
    <link href="http://ruthienachmany.github.io/blog/2013/06/13/mediumsyouthinkin/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-13T00:23:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://ruthienachmany.github.io/blog/2013/06/13/mediumsyouthinkin</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>text editor</p>

<p>testing</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Our Speakers]]></title>
    <link href="http://ruthienachmany.github.io/blog/2013/06/12/our-speakers/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-12T20:15:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://ruthienachmany.github.io/blog/2013/06/12/our-speakers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Gwen Bell</p>

<p>Matt Hackett</p>

<p>Jeff Casimir</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[First Nine Days]]></title>
    <link href="http://ruthienachmany.github.io/blog/2013/06/12/first-nine-days/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-12T20:14:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://ruthienachmany.github.io/blog/2013/06/12/first-nine-days</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Collage]]></title>
    <link href="http://ruthienachmany.github.io/blog/2013/06/12/collage/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-12T20:14:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://ruthienachmany.github.io/blog/2013/06/12/collage</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[GUI]]></title>
    <link href="http://ruthienachmany.github.io/blog/2013/06/12/roo/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-12T19:54:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://ruthienachmany.github.io/blog/2013/06/12/roo</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Practice Failure]]></title>
    <link href="http://ruthienachmany.github.io/blog/2013/06/09/hello-world/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-09T16:19:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://ruthienachmany.github.io/blog/2013/06/09/hello-world</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Language]]></title>
    <link href="http://ruthienachmany.github.io/blog/2013/06/09/hiiii/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-09T13:39:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://ruthienachmany.github.io/blog/2013/06/09/hiiii</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Visualizing Github]]></title>
    <link href="http://ruthienachmany.github.io/blog/2013/06/05/ruby-chard-images/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-05T11:05:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://ruthienachmany.github.io/blog/2013/06/05/ruby-chard-images</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Abstraction]]></title>
    <link href="http://ruthienachmany.github.io/blog/2013/06/05/hello/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-05T10:39:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://ruthienachmany.github.io/blog/2013/06/05/hello</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
